you
Krishnamurti in dialogue with Dr. Alan
W. Anderson. J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England. For
the past 40 years he has been speaking
in the United States, Europe, India,
Australia, and other parts of the world.
From the outset of his life's
work he repudiated all connections with organized
religions and ideologies and said that
his only concern was to set men
absolutely unconditionally free. He is the
author of many books, among them the
Awakening of Intelligence, the Urgency of
Change, Freedom from the Known, and the
Flight of the Eagle. This is one
of a series of dialogues between Krishnamurti
and Dr. Alan W. Anderson, who
is professor of religious studies at San
Diego State University where he teaches
Indian and Chinese scriptures and the
oracular tradition. Dr. Anderson, a
published poet, received his degree from
Columbia University and the Union
Theological Seminary. He has been honored
with a Distinguished Teaching Award
from the California State Universities.
As Krishnamurti, last time we were
speaking together we were going into
beauty and just as we came to the
end of our conversation the question of seeing
and its relation to the transformation
of man, which is not dependent on
knowledge or time, was something we
promised ourselves we would we would
take up next time we could come together.
That is,
sir, what is seeing and what is listening
and what is learning? I think there are
three related to each other, learning, hearing and seeing.
What is seeing, perceiving?
Do we actually see? Or do
we see through a screen, darkly?
Screen of prejudice, screen of
our idiosyncrasies, experiences, our wishes,
pleasures, fears, and obviously our images
about that which we see and about
ourselves. So we have these screen after
screen between us and the object of
perception. So do we ever see the thing
at all? Or is it the seeing is coming
at all? Or is it the seeing
is coloured by our knowledge, botanical experience,
so on, so on, so on, or our images
which we have about that thing, or the belief
in which the mind is
conditioned and therefore prevents the seeing?
Or is the memories which the mind
has cultivated prevents the seeing? So seeing
may not take place at all.
And is it possible for the mind
not to have these images, conclusions, beliefs,
memories, prejudices, fears, and without
having those screens, just to look?
I think this becomes very important because
when there is a seeing of the thing
which I am talking about, when there
is a seeing you can't help but acting.
There is no question of postponement.
Or succession, or interval.
Because when action is based on a belief,
a conclusion, an idea, then that action is
time-binding. And that action will inevitably
bring conflict and sorrow, regrets and all
the rest of it. So it becomes very important
to find out what it is to see, to perceive,
what it is to hear. Do I ever hear? When
one is married, as a wife or a husband, or a
girl or boy, do I ever hear her or him?
Or I hear her or him through the image I have
built about her or him, through the
screen of irritations, screen of annoyance, domination,
all that, that dreadful things that come in relationship.
So, do I ever hear directly
what you say, without translating, without transforming
it, without twisting it? Do I ever hear a bird
cry or a child weep or a man crying in
pain? You follow, sir? Do I ever hear anything?
In a conversation we had about a year ago,
I was very struck by something you said, which
I regard as for myself personally, immensely
valuable. You said that hearing was doing
nothing to stop or interfere with seeing.
Hearing is doing nothing to stop seeing.
That is very remarkable because in conversation
the notion of hearing is regarded as intimately
associated with command. We will say, won't we,
now hear me, hear me out. And the person
thinks that they have to lean forward in
the sense of do something voluntarily. It's as
though they have to screw themselves up into
some sort of agonized twist here, not only
to please the one who is insisting that they
are not hearing, but to get up some hearing
on their own. Yes, yes.
So, does a human being, I, O, X, listen
at all? And what takes place when I do listen?
Listen in the sense, without any
interference, without any interpretation, conclusion, like
and dislike, you know, all that takes
place. What happens when I actually listen? Sir,
look, we said just now we cannot possibly
understand what beauty is if we don't understand
suffering, passion. You hear that statement. What
does the mind do? It draws a conclusion.
It has formed an idea, verbal idea, words,
hears the words, draws a conclusion and an
idea, a statement of that kind, has become an
idea. Then the mind says, how am I to
carry out that idea? And that becomes a problem.
Of course it does, because the idea doesn't
conform to nature, and other people have other
ideas, and they want to get theirs
embodied, now we are up against a clash.
Yes. So, can I listen to that, can
the mind listen to that statement without any forming
an abstraction? Just listen. And either
agreeing or disagree, just actually listen completely
to that statement.
If I am following you, what you are saying
is that were I to listen adequately, or just,
let's say, listen, because it is not a
question of more or less, I am absolutely listening,
or I am absolutely not listening.
I would not have to contrive an answer.
No, because you are in it.
So, like the cat, the action and
the seeing are one. They are one act.
That's right.
One act.
That's right. So, can I listen to a statement,
and see the truth of the statement, or the
falseness of the statement, not in comparison, but
in the very statement that you are making?
I don't know if I am making myself clear.
Yes, you are making yourself very clear.
That is, I listen to the statement,
beauty can never exist without passion, and passion
comes from sorrow. I listen to that statement. I
don't abstract an idea of it, or make an
idea from it. I just listen. What takes place?
You may be telling the truth, or you may be
making a false statement. I don't know,
because I am not going to compare.
No, you are going to see.
I just listen, which means I am giving
my total attention. Just listen to this, sir.
You see what is going to happen. I give
my total attention to what you are saying. Then
it doesn't matter what you say or don't say.
You see?
Of course.
What is important is my act of listening.
And that act of listening has brought about
a miracle of complete freedom from all
your statements, whether they are true, false,
real, my mind is completely attentive. Attention means
no border. The moment I have a border,
I begin to fight you, agree, disagree.
The moment attention has a frontier, then concepts
arise. But if I listen to you completely
without a single interference of thought or ideation,
or commentation, just listen to that, the
miracle has taken place. Which is, my total
attention absorbs me, my mind, from all the
statements. I don't know if I am correct.
Therefore my mind is extraordinarily free to act.
Well, this has happened for me on this
series of our conversations. With each one of these
conversations, since this is being videotaped, one
begins when one is given the sign, and
we are told when the time has elapsed.
And one ordinarily, in terms of activity in this
sort, is thinking about the production as such.
But one of the things that I have learned
in our conversation, I have been listening very
intensely, and yet I have not had to
divide my mind. And yet this is, if I
am responding correctly to what you have been teaching me,
what you have been teaching – well, I
know you don't like that word, what you have
been saying, and I understand why teaching was
a wrong word here. There is that very
first encounter that the mind engages itself in.
How can I afford not to make the distinction
between paying attention to the aspects of
the program on the production aspect of it
and still engage our discussion? But the
more intensely the discussion is engaged, the
more efficiently all the mechanism is accomplished.
We don't believe that, in the sense that
not only to start with will we not believe
it, but we won't even try it out. There
is no guarantee from anybody in advance. What
we are told, rather, is this. Well, you get
used to it, and yet performers have stage
fright all their lives, so clearly they don't
get used to it.
No, sir, it is... Because, sir, don't you
think it is, our minds are so commercial.
Unless I get a reward from it, I won't
do a thing. My mind lives in the market place,
one's mind. I give you this, give me that.
A. And there is an interval in between.
K. Right.
You follow? We are so used to
commercialism, both spiritually and physically, that we don't
do anything without a reward, without gaining
something, without a purpose. It all must
be exchanged. Not a gift, but exchange. I give
you this, and you give me that. I torture
myself religiously, and God must come to
me. It is all a matter of commerce.
A. Commas?
K. Fundamentalists have a phrase that comes
to mind with respect to their devotional
life. They say, I am claiming the promises
of God. And this phrase, in the context of
what you are saying, is, my goodness,
what that couldn't lead to in the mind.
I know, sir. So, you see, one goes very
deeply into this. When action is not based on an
idea, formula, belief, then seeing is the
doing, then what is seeing and hearing, which
we went into, then the seeing is complete
attention, and the doing is in that attention.
And the difficulty is, people will
ask, how will you maintain that attention?
A. Yes, and they haven't even started.
K. Yes, no, how will you maintain it?
A. Yes.
K. Which means they are looking for a reward.
A. Exactly.
K. I will practise it. I will do
anything to maintain that attention in order to get
something in return. Attention is not a result.
Attention has no cause. I mean, what has cause
has an effect, and the effect becomes
the cause. It's a circle. But attention isn't
that. Attention doesn't give you a reward.
Attention, on the contrary, there is no reward
or punishment, because there is no frontier.
A. Yes, this calls up an earlier conversation
we had when you mentioned the word virtue,
and we explored it in relation to power.
K. Exactly.
A. And we are told what is difficult
for a thinking child to believe, given the way
the child is brought up, but he is required
somehow to make his way through it, that virtue
is its own reward.
And of course it's impossible to see
what is sound about that under the conditioned
situation in which he lives.
K. That's just an idea, sir.
A. It's an idea. So now we tuck that
back, and then later when we need to remind somebody
that they are asking too much of a reward
for something good that they did, we tell them,
well, have you forgotten that virtue is its
own reward? Yes, yes, it becomes a form of
punishment.
K. So then, you see, seeing and hearing,
then what is learning? Because they are all interrelated
– learning, seeing, hearing, action and all
that. It's all in one movement. They
are not separate chapters. It's one chapter.
A. Distinctions, no divisions.
K. So what is learning? Is learning
a process of accumulation? And is learning non-accumulative?
We are putting both together. Wait
a minute, let's look at it.
One learns a language, Italian, French, whatever
it is, and accumulates words, and the irregular
words and so on, and then able to speak.
There is learning a language and being able to speak.
Learning how to ride a bicycle, learning how
to drive a car, learning how to put together
a machine, electronics and so on and so
on. Those are all learning to acquire knowledge
in action. And I am asking, is there any
other form of learning? That we know. We are familiar
with the acquisition of knowledge. Now is
there any other kind of learning? Learning which
is not accumulated and acting. I don't know if you...
A. Yes, when we have accumulated it
all we haven't understood anything on that account.
Yes. And I learn in order to gain a
reward, or in order to avoid punishment. I learn a
particular job, a particular craft in order
to earn a livelihood. That is absolutely necessary.
Otherwise... Now, I am asking, is there any
other kind of learning? That is routine. That
is the cultivation of memory, and the memory,
which is the result of experience and knowledge,
that is stored in the brain and that operates.
When asked to do, ride a bicycle, drive a
car and so on.
拿
Is there any other kind of learning, or only that?
When one says, I have learnt from my experience,
it means I have learnt,
stored up from that experience certain memories,
and those memories either prevent, reward, or punish.
So, then all such forms of learning are mechanical.
And the brain and education is trained,
education is to train the brain to function in routine,
mechanically, because in that there is great security.
Then it is safe.
And so our mind becomes mechanical.
My father did this, I do this, you follow?
The whole business is mechanical.
Now, is there a non-mechanical brain at all?
A non-utilitarian, in that sense,
learning which has neither future nor past,
therefore not time-binding.
I don't know if I am making this...
A.S. – Don't we sometimes say,
I have learnt from experience,
when we wish to convey something
that isn't well conveyed by that expression,
we wish to convey an insight
that we don't feel can
be, in a strict sense, dated?
K.R. – Yes, sir. You see, sir,
do we learn anything from experience?
We have had, from history, history began, written history,
five thousand wars.
I read somewhere, five thousand wars,
killing, killing, killing, maimed.
And have we learnt anything?
Have we learnt anything from sorrow?
Man has suffered.
Have we learnt anything from experience,
the agony of uncertainty and all the rest of it?
So when we say we
have learnt, I question, you follow?
It seems such a terrible thing to say,
I have learnt from experience.
You have learnt nothing,
except in the field of knowledge.
I don't know...
A.S. – Yes, may I say
something here that just passed in recall?
We were talking about sorrow before,
and I was thinking of a statement
of St Paul's in his letter to the Romans,
where there's a very unusual sequence of words,
where he says, we rejoice in tribulations.
Now, some people have thought
he must have been a masochist
or something in making such a statement,
but that certainly seems to me bizarre.
We rejoice in tribulations.
And then he says, because tribulation works,
and in the Greek this means that there's energy involved,
works patience, patience experience.
Now, that's a very unusual order,
because we usually think that if we have enough experience,
we'll learn to be patient.
And he completely stands that on its head.
And in the context of what you're saying,
that order of his words makes eminent sense.
Please go on.
K. No, no, I'll go ahead.
A. Yes, that's really very remarkable.
K. You see, sir, that's why our education, our civilisation,
all the things about us,
has made our minds so mechanical,
so repetitive reactions,
repetitive demands, repetitive pursuits,
same thing being repeated year after year,
thousands of years,
my country in your country,
I'll kill you, you kill me.
You follow, sir? The whole thing is mechanical.
Now, that means the mind can never be free.
Thought is never free.
Thought is always old.
There is no new thought.
A. No, it's very curious in relation to a movement
within the field of religion that calls itself,
or did call itself, new thought.
I was laughing at the irony of it.
Yes, goodness me.
Some persons, I imagine, would object to the notion
that we don't learn from experience
in terms of the succession of wars,
because wars tend to happen sequentially,
generation to generation, and you have to grow up.
But that's not true, because wars,
more than one war will happen very often
in the same generation.
K. Listen, what are they talking about?
Two wars.
A. Yes, hasn't been anything learned at all.
At all.
It's a terrifying thing to hear
someone just come out and say,
nobody learns anything from experience.
K. No, the word experience also means to go through.
A. Yes.
K. But you never go through.
A. That's exactly right.
K. You always stop in
the middle, or you never begin.
A. Right.
It means, if I'm remembering correctly
in terms of its radical root,
it means to test, to put to test,
to, well, to put a thing to the test
and behave correctly while that's going on.
You simply have to. You
see, you just have to look.
Don't you?
Yes.
K. So, as our civilisation, our culture,
our education has brought about a mind
that is becoming more and more mechanical,
and therefore time-binding,
and therefore never a sense of freedom.
Freedom then becomes an idea,
you play around philosophically, but it's no meaning.
But a man who says,
now, I want to find out,
I want to really go into this
and discover if there is freedom,
then he has to understand the limits of knowledge.
Where knowledge ends,
or rather, the ending of knowledge
and the beginning of something totally new.
I don't know if I'm conveying anything.
A. You are. Oh, yes.
K. That is, sir, what is learning?
If it is not mechanical, then what is learning?
Is there a learning at all? Learning about what?
I learn how to go to the moon,
how to put up this,
that, and drive, and so on.
In that field there is only learning.
Is there any learning in any other field,
psychologically, spiritually?
Can the mind learn about what they call God?
A. If in learning,
in the sense that you have asked this question
– no, I must rephrase that, stop this if-ing –
when one does what I'm about to say,
when one learns about God, or going to the moon,
in terms of the question you've asked,
he can't be doing what you are pointing to
if this is something added on to the list.
K. Sir, look, it's so clear. A. Yes, it is.
K. I learn a language,
ride a bicycle, drive a car, put a machine together,
that's essential.
Now, I want to learn
about God. Just listen to me.
God is my making.
God hasn't made me in his image.
Ha ha ha ha.
I have made him in my image,
and I am going to learn about him.
A. Yes, I am going to talk to myself.
K. Yes, learn about the image which I have built,
about Christ, Buddha, whatever it is,
the image I have built.
So I am learning what?
A. To talk about talk.
K. Learning about the image which I have built.
Therefore is there any other kind of learning
except mechanical learning?
I don't know if I...
You understand my question?
A. Yes, I do. Yes, I do. I certainly do.
K. So there is only learning
the mechanical process of life.
There is no other learning.
See what that means, sir.
A. It means freedom.
K. I can learn about myself.
Because myself is known.
I may not know it, but I can know
by looking at myself I can know myself.
So the myself is the accumulated knowledge of the past.
The me who says, I am greedy, I am envy,
I am successful, I am frightened,
I am betrayed, I regret, all that is the me,
including the soul which I have invented in the me.
The Brahman, the Atman, it's all me still.
The me has created the image of God
and I am going to learn
about God, which has no meaning.
So, if there is...
I am going to use the word if.
If there is no other learning, what takes place?
You understand?
The mind is used in
the acquisition of knowledge in matter
– we'll put it differently –
in mechanical things.
And when the mind is employed there,
is there any other process of learning?
Which means psychologically, inwardly.
Is there?
The inward is the invention of
thought as opposed to the outer.
Right, don't you follow?
If I have understood the
outer, I have understood the inner,
because the inner has created the outer.
The outer in the sense of the structure, the society,
the religious sanctions, all that is invented
or put together by thought.
The Jesuses, the Christ, the Buddhas, you follow? All that.
And what is there to learn?
A. In listening to you...
K. See the beauty of
what is coming out of it.
A. Oh, yes, yes.
It goes back to your remark about Vedanta
as the end of knowledge.
K. That's what I was told.
A. Yes. The interesting thing to me
about the Sanskrit construction is that
unless I am mistaken,
it doesn't mean the end of
it as a terminus, as a term,
because that would simply start a new series.
It's the consummation of it, which is the total end
in the sense that a totally new beginning is made
at that very point.
K. That means, sir, I know,
the mind knows the activity of the known.
A. That's right, yes.
That's the consummation of knowledge.
Of knowledge.
Now, what is the state of the mind
that is free from that, and yet functions in knowledge?
A. And yet functions in it.
Yes, yes. It is seeing perfectly.
K. Go into it, you'll see,
very strange things take place.
Is this possible, first?
You understand, sir?
Because the brain functions mechanically.
It wants security,
otherwise it can't function.
If we hadn't security,
we wouldn't be here sitting together.
Because we have security, we can have a dialogue.
The brain can only function in complete security,
whether that security it finds in a neurotic belief,
or in a neurotic belief,
all beliefs and all ideas are neurotic in that sense,
so it finds it somewhere,
in accepting nationality is the highest form of the good.
Success is the highest virtue.
That's all. It finds belief, security there.
Now, you are asking the brain,
which has become mechanical, trained, century,
to see the other field which is not mechanical.
Is there another field?
A. No.
K. You follow my question?
A. Yes, that's what's so utterly devastating.
K. Wait, wait. Is there another field?
Now, unless the brain and
the mind understands the whole field,
understands the movement of knowledge,
it is a movement.
A. It's a movement, yes.
K. It's not just static.
You are adding, taking away, putting it, and so on.
Unless it understands all that,
it cannot possibly ask that other question.
A. Exactly.
K. And when it does
ask that question, what takes place?
Sir, this is real meditation, you understand?
A. Yes.
K. Which we will go into another time.
So, you see, that's what it means.
One is always listening with knowledge,
seeing with knowledge.
A. This is the seeing through a glass, darkly.
K. Darkly.
Now, is there a listening out of silence?
And that is attention.
And that is not time-binding,
because in that silence I don't want anything.
It isn't I am going to learn about myself,
it isn't I am going to be punished or rewarded.
In that absolute silence I listen.
A. The wonder of the whole thing is that
it isn't something that is
done, this meditation, in succession.
K. Sir, when we talk about meditation,
we will have to go very deeply into that,
because they have destroyed that word,
these shoddy little men coming from India or anywhere,
they have destroyed that thing.
A. I heard the other day about someone
who was learning transcendental meditation.
K. Oh, learning. You follow the song?
A. Of course.
And they had to do it
at three o'clock in the afternoon.
K. Paid $35 or $100 to learn that.
So sacrilegious.
A. But if, that is, three o'clock in the afternoon
was judgment day.
If you didn't do it according to your schedule,
then the world has obviously come to an end.
But ostensibly you are doing
it to get free of that.
Do go ahead.
K. So you see, sir, that is what takes place.
We began this morning about beauty,
then passion, then suffering, then action.
Action based on idea is inaction.
It sounds monstrous, but there it is.
And from that we said, what
is seeing and what is hearing?
The seeing and the listening has become mechanical.
We never see anything new.
Even the flower is never new,
which has blossomed overnight.
We say, yes, that is the
rose, I have been expecting it,
it has come out now, how beautiful.
It is always from the known to the known.
A movement in time and therefore time-binding,
and therefore never free.
And yet we are talking about freedom,
philosophy, the lectures on freedom, and so on, so on.
And the communists call it
a bourgeois thing, which it is,
in the sense, when you limit it to knowledge,
it is foolish to talk about freedom.
But there is a freedom
when you understand the movement of knowledge.
So can you observe out of silence,
and observe and act in the field of knowledge,
both together in harmony?
A.M. Seeing, then, is not scheduled.
Yes, of course.
What a...
Yes, sir.
I was just thinking about the...
I suppose you would say a classical definition of freedom
in terms of the career of knowledge,
would be that it is a property of action,
a property or quality of action,
for general uses, either word would do,
property or quality.
And it occurred to me,
in the context of what we have been saying,
what a horror that one could read that statement,
and not let it disclose itself to you.
If it disclosed itself to you,
you would be up against it.
You would have to be serious.
If you were a philosophy student and you read that,
and that thing began to operate in you,
you would say,
I have got to get
this settled before I go on,
maybe I will never graduate.
That is not important.
K. That is not important, quite right.
And I was thinking,
in the West as well as in the East,
you have to go to the factory or the office,
the factory or the office every day of your life.
Get up at nine o'clock, eight o'clock, six o'clock,
drive, walk, work, work, work,
for fifty years, routine,
and get kicked about, insulted,
worship success, again repetition,
and occasionally talk about God if it is convenient,
and so on and so on.
That is a monstrous life.
And that is what we are educating our children for.
A. That is the real living death.
K. And nobody says,
for God's sake, let's look
at all this, I am new.
Let's wipe our eyes clear of the past
and look what we are doing,
give attention, care what we are doing.
A. No, we have this question instead.
What shall we do about it?
Yes, that is the question.
And then that becomes the next thing done.
K. Which is the continuity of
the past in a different form.
A. And the chain is
endlessly linked, linked, linked, linked.
Cause becoming the effect and the effect becoming the cause.
So it is a very serious
thing when we talk about all this,
because life becomes dreadfully serious.
And it is only this serious person that lives,
not these people who seek entertainment,
religious or otherwise.
A. I had a very interesting occasion
to understand what you are saying in class yesterday.
I was trying to assist the students to see that
the classical understanding of the four causes in operation
is that they are non-temporarily related.
And I said when the potter
puts his hand to the clay,
the hand touching the clay is
not responded to by the clay
after the hand has touched it.
And one person who was visiting the class,
this person was a well-educated person
and a professor.
And this struck them as maybe not so.
And I could tell by the expression on the face
that there was this little anguish here.
So I said, well, my radar says
that there is some difficulty going on.
What is the matter?
Well, it seems like there is a time interval.
So I asked them to pick
something up that was on the desk,
and I said, well, now touch it with your finger
and tell me at the moment
of the touching with the finger
whether the thing reacts to the finger after it's touched.
Now, do it.
Well, even to ask somebody to
apply a practical test like that
with respect to a datum of knowledge,
about the four causes, or...
is to interrupt the process
of education as we've known it,
because you teach a student about the four causes
and he thinks about them.
He never goes out and looks at a thing
or does anything about it.
And so we spent about...
well, we were picking stuff up in class
and we were doing this until finally
it seemed like a revelation
that what has been said
in the classical teaching of it,
which of course in modern society is rejected,
happens to be the case.
And I said, this has to be seen.
Seen, what?
This is what you mean.
Of course, of course.
But we're back to that step there.
Why was that person,
and so many other students following suit,
anguished at the point where the practical issue arose?
There was a feeling, I suppose,
that they were on the cliff.
Quite, quite.
And naturally alertness was required,
but alertness registers that we're on a cliff.
Quite.
So therefore the best thing to
do is turn around and run back.
Yes, yes.
Sir, I think you see,
we are so caught up in words.
To us the word is not the thing.
The description is not the description.
Not described.
To us the description is all that matters.
Because we are slaves to words.
And to ritual.
Ritual and all the rest of it.
So when you say,
look, the thing matters more than the word,
and then they say, how am
I to get rid of the word?
How am I to communicate if I have no word?
You see how they've gone off?
They're not concerned with the thing, but with the word.
Yes.
The door is not the word.
So when you are caught up in words,
the word door becomes extraordinarily important.
And not the door.
And I don't really need to
come to terms with the door,
I say to myself, because I have the word.
Exactly.
I have it all.
So education has done this.
A great part of this
education is the acceptance of words
as an abstraction from the fact, from the what is.
All philosophies are based on that.
Theorise, theorise, theorise endlessly,
how one should live.
And the philosopher himself doesn't live.
You see this all over.
A. Yes, I know, especially some philosophies
that have seemed to me quite bizarre in this respect.
I've asked my colleagues from time to time,
well, if you believe that
stuff, why don't you do it?
And they look at me as
though I'm out of my mind,
as though nobody would really seriously ask that question.
But if you can't ask that question,
well, what question is worth asking?
Quite right.
Yes.
A. I was thinking about that marvellous story
you told in our previous conversation about the monkey
while you were speaking about this.
When she shook hands with you,
nobody had told her how to shake hands.
K. No, it stretched out.
A. Yes.
K. When I took it.
A. Wasn't something that she was taught how to do
through a verbal communication.
It was the appropriate thing at the time
without anyone measuring its appropriateness.
K. Quite.
A. Isn't that something?
A. Yes.
I can't tell you how grateful I am
to have been able to share this with you.
I've seen in respect to
my own activity as a teacher
where I must perform therapy even on my language
so that I don't give
the student an occasion for thinking
that I am simply adding to this endless chain,
link after link after link.
There are two therapies here then.
There's the therapy that relates to words
and that flows out naturally.
It's not a contrivance.
It flows out naturally, if I've understood you correctly,
from the therapy within.
Now this relates directly, as you were saying earlier,
to meditation. Are we ready?
K. I think that's too complicated.
A. I don't mean right now,
but maybe in one of our next conversations we could...
K. We must discuss several things here, sir.
What is love, what is death, what is meditation,
what is the whole movement of living?
We've got a great deal to do.
A. Oh, I do look
forward very much to that. Splendid.